Finding Aid for the Carey McWilliams Correspondence LSC.2448
UCLA Library Special Collections
Carey McWilliams correspondence
1924-1975
1924-1950
UCLA Library Special Collections
McWilliams, Carey
LSC.2448
1.0 linear feet (2 boxes)
Carey McWilliams (1905-1980) was a writer, lawyer, journalist, lecturer, activist, as well as Chief of the California Division of Immigration and Housing (1938-1942) and editor of The Nation (1955-1975). This collection contains correspondence, primarily letters written to McWilliams.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Wilson Carey McWilliams, June 2004.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9953906233606533
Biography
Carey McWilliams was born December 13, 1905 in Steamboat Springs, Colorado. He completed his Juris Doctorate from the University of Southern California in 1927. From 1927-1938, McWilliams was an attorney at the law firm Black, Hammack in Los Angeles. In 1938, he was appointed as Chief of the Division of Immigration and Housing of the State of California, a position he kept until 1942. During the period from 1945-1955, he began his long association with The Nation, becoming successively contributing editor, associate editor, and then editorial director. From 1955-1975, he was The Nation's editor. In addition to his editorial duties, McWilliams was a prolific lecturer and writer, speaking on many subjects and contributing articles and essays to numerous publications. After his retirement from The Nation, he continued to write a regular column for that publication. His monographs include Ambrose Bierce, a biography (1929); Louis Adamic and shadow America (1935); Factories in the field: the story of migratory farm labor in California (1939); Ill fares the land: migrants and migratory labor in the United States (1942); Brothers under the skin (1943); Prejudice: Japanese-Americans, symbol of racial intolerance (1944); Southern California country: an island on the land (1946); A mask for privilege: anti-Semitism in America (1948); North from Mexico: the Spanish-speaking people of the United States (1949); California: the great exception (1949); Witch hunt: the revival of heresy (1950); and his autobiography The education of Carey McWilliams (1979). In the late 1970s, McWilliams was briefly a Regents Lecturer at the University of California Riverside and then taught one quarter at the University of California Los Angeles in the History Department. He died of cancer at the age of 74 on June 27, 1980 in New York, New York.
Scope and Content
The collection contains Carey McWilliams's correspondence, primarily letters that were written to him. Many of the letters are from writers mentioning reviews or articles he composed about their work. Some of them discuss future writings or McWilliams's work on topics such as Ambrose Bierce, Louis Adamic, George Sterling, and western regionalism. The collection also contains fan mail, letters addressing McWilliams's research or political causes, some of McWilliams's responses, and assorted supporting materials.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence.
Related Material
Carey McWilliams Papers (Collection 1319). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams Papers - Card Files (Collection 1243). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Collection of materials by and about George Sterling (Collection 276). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams Collection of Material about Mary Hunter Austin (Collection 278). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams Collection of Material about Ambrose Bierce (Collection 277). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams papers (Collection BANC MSS C-H 46). Available at Bancroft Library, UC Berkeley.
Carey McWilliams miscellaneous papers. Available at Hoover Institution Archives, Stanford, CA.
The following oral history is available through the UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research:
Interview of Carey McWilliams
Honorable in all things: the memoirs of Carey McWilliams [oral history transcript] / Carey McWilliams, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, c1982. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Periodical editors -- United States -- Archives.; McWilliams, Carey -- Archives
- Correspondence, 1924-1975 (bulk 1924-1950); 2 boxes (1 linear foot)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of correspondence. Files are arranged alphabetically by the surname of the correspondent, in respect to the original order. In each folder, letters are arranged chronologically with undated ones filed at the beginning. Unidentified correspondents are located at the end of the series, as is a folder of miscellaneous printed materials.
  - American Jewish Committee, 1948; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Letter from McWilliams, a joint memorandum, and a 7-page typewritten manuscript entitled "Memorandum" by McWilliams.
  - American Red Cross, 1946; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence with McWilliams.
  - Appell, George, 1946 July; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Baldwin, Roger, 1945-1946; 6 items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bancroft, Hubert Howe, 1946 July; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beardsley, Helen and Charles E., 1946 August; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bunzel, Jack, 1949 September 18; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Card to McWilliams.
  - California State Library, 1936; 5 items. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes related materials on California's poet laureates.
  - Carlson, Evans, 1945 September 11; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carson, Charles A., 1949 December; 5 items. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chandler, Norman, 1931, October 3; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chapman, Oscar, 1949 November 30; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cohn, Morris, 1944; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Letter from McWilliams, and a clipping concerning Judge Goodwin Knight.
  - Collier, John, 1934, 1942; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes printed materials dealing with the Mission Indian Federation.
  - Cushman, Rober E., 1950, August 4; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Danton, George H., 1948 August 25; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Davis, H.L., 1930; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dienstein, William, 1948 July 15; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dobie, Charles Caldwell, 1930-1933; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dumont, Henry, 1935-1936; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Elias, Robert H., 1939 August 5; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Federal Parole Board, 1950 August 24; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Letter from McWilliams concerning Alvah Bessie's parole.
  - Fee, Marcia Gayle, 1926; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fenelon, Eugenie, 1928 January 12; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Fenton, Frank, undated; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Fergusson, Erna, 1949 January 10; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Fergusson, Harvey, ca. 1940; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Field, Sara Bard, 1929; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Firkins, O.W., 1931 January 13; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Foote, Mary Hallock, 1930-1936; 9 items. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes typewritten notes on and quotations from her books.
  - Francis, R.W., 1932, November 18; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gallagher, Leo, 1935 October 20; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Gidlow, Elsa, 1937 June 16; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Godard, Howard, 1938 June 18; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gray, H.D., 1925 March 4; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Gudenian, Haig, 1935; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Includes a publicity brochure on Gudenian.
  - Hadley, J. Nixon, 1943; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Haines, Paul, 1934; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Includes typewritten notes.
  - Hanna, Phil Townsend, 1934-1935; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Hart, James D., 1930-1932; 20 items. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Hazlitt, Henry, 1933 August 7; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Hergesheimer, Joseph, 1929 February 11; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hicks, Granville, 1930; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Higgins, F.R., 1931-1932; 14 items. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Correspondence with and concerning Higgins. Also includes a clipping, and typewritten and signed copies of Higgins's poems.
  - Hogan, Edward, 1939 August 17; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Holt, Madora, 1935 December 4; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Hood, Juliette, 1937 June 14; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Hubbell, Jay B., 1930 February 11; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Hughes, Glenn, 1929 November 25; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - James, E., 1924 July 18; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Johnson, Harold R., 1936; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Johnson, Lucius W., 1937 June; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Johnson, Roosevelt, 1930; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Johnstone, Helen Louise, 1946 October 8; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Jones, Idwal, 1929-1939; 7 items. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Also includes 1 letter from Phil Townsend Hanna to McWilliams and 1 letter from Hanna to Jones.
  - Jones, Nard, 1929-1934; 20 items. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Also includes 1 clipping, and an image of Jones.
  - Josephson, Matthew, 1975 February 13; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Kaplan, J.M., 1947-1948; 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Also includes an article about the Welch Grape Juice Company.
  - Kelly, Mr., 1948 March 14; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    6 page letter from McWilliams concerning the publicity for North from Mexico.
  - Klein, Herb, 1931-1933; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kramer, Dale D., undated; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Krutch, Joseph Wood, 1925-1930; 5 items. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - La Motte, Ellen Newbold, 1929; 5 items. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lavrin, Janko, 1930-1935; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Le Sueur, M., undated; 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Leary, Mary Ellen, undated; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Leckenby, Maurice, undated; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Includes a letter of recommendation for McWilliams.
  - Lengyel, Cornel, 1943; 7 items. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Includes typewritten copies of Lengyel's poems.
  - Lewis, Janet, 1930 July 9; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Lewis, Oscar, 1929-1930, 1974; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Lloyd, J. William, 1930-1931; 7 items. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Long, H., 1930 October 15; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ludovin, Anthony, 1924 September 9; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - MacKaye, James, 1932 August 7; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Mayo, Morrow, 1929; 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - McCarthy, John R., 1929-1933; 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - McCoy, Frank J., 1938 April 16; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Concerning Horace A. Vachell's books.
  - Merriam, H.G., 1928-1934; 16 items. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Also includes indexes to The Frontier: a magazine of the Northwest, and a program.
  - Miscellaneous materials, 1935, 1942; 7 items. (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Report on importation of Negro labor to California prepared by McWilliams as Chief of the Division of Immigration and Housing. Also contains a clipping on Henry Lafler, an essay "Benjamin DeCasseres: a fourth dimensional mind" by S.P. Rudens, a typewritten poem "The night court" by Ruth Comfort Mitchell, and ten black and white (approximately) 3.5 x 4 photographs of Lloyd at Roscoe.
  - Monaghan, Frank, 1929-1935; 9 items. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Moore, Wm. E., 1934-1935; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Moore was the managing editor of The Sun.
  - Nakazawa, Ken, 1929-1935; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Includes a clipping.
  - Nathan, Otto, 1947; 9 items. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Includes a memorandum, correspondence between Nathan and Margaret O'Connor, and a resume. These materials relate to fund-raising for Harold Laski.
  - Niven, Frederick, 1930; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Nussbaum, Olga, 1940 August 5; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Pearce, Charles A., 1932 March 15; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Letter to Maxim Lieber concerning McWilliams.
  - Phipps, Margaret R., 1950 January 3; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Powell, William Clark, 1937-1938; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Letters to McWilliams concerning a column he wrote on Will Levington Comfort.
  - Purdy, James, 1972-1973; 5 items. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Correspondence with McWilliams. Includes a press release and a clipping.
  - Rourke, Constance, 1931 May 4; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Ryan, Don, 1929-1930; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Smith, Paul, 1950 August 31; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Letter from McWilliams.
  - Stevens, James, 1925-1926; 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Stewart, George R. Jr., 1931-1936; 6 items. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Stolberg, Benjamin, 1930-1935; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Tracy, Henry C., 1929-1936; 16 items. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Also includes 1 letter from McWilliams.
  - Unidentified correspondents, 1930-1931; 5 items. (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - United States Atomic Energy Commission, 1949; 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Vachell, Horace Annesley, 1938 March 14; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Wallace, William Kay, 1933 April 8; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Watson, E.L. Grant, 1930; 6 items. (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Also includes an article by Watson, and a brochure on his lectures.
  - Watterson, Elsie, 1930; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Includes a letter from the California State Prison to McWilliams.
  - Weisberg, Goldie, 1929-1931; 7 items. (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Includes 2 letters from McWilliams to publishers, and a clipping.
  - Weisz, George, 1949 April 26; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Welch, Marie de L., 1929; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Includes clippings of Welch's poems.
  - West, G., 1930 August; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Whipple, T.K., 1931; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Winter, Ella, undated; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Wydra, Miriam, 1943 August; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Young, A. Beatrice, 1940-1941; 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 53)